<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-10-20T05:45:41+00:00</updated><id>https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//feed.xml</id><title type="html">Stephanie M. Wyatt</title><subtitle>Minister | Community Builder | Teacher-Scholar</subtitle><entry><title type="html">My Life in Books</title><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//my-life-books/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Life in Books" /><published>2022-10-19T08:23:42+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-19T08:23:42+00:00</updated><id>https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//my-life-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//my-life-books/"><![CDATA[<p>A few years ago I heard a radio interview on NPR with an author of a novel in which the narrator introduces each character in terms of three books that best describes him or her. I pondered this idea in search of three books that would form a composite image of who I am and what my values are. I selected Jane Austen’s <em>Pride and Prejudice</em>, Philip Halle’s <em>Lest Innocent Blood Be Shed</em>, and Christopher Hill’s <em>Holidays and Holy Nights</em>.</p>

<p><em>Pride and Prejudice</em> by Jane Austen is a novel of the British Regency period and is considered by many to be a great work of English literature. Like Jane Austen, I am simultaneously a romantic and a pragmatist. I love a happy ending, but I realize that happy endings are often hard won. For better and for worse, one’s choices in life are shaped by numerous familial, societal, and financial considerations. The novel’s hero, Elizabeth Bennett, possesses several qualities that I also see in myself. She is smart, clever, personable, persistent, and fiercely loyal. The original title of the novel was <em>First Impressions</em>, because it explores the relationship between our surface perceptions of other people upon first meeting them and the substance of the character that may reside underneath their public persona. Through the course of the novel Elizabeth Bennett and her romantic opposite, Fitzwilliam Darcy, discover that snap judgments can lead to false conclusions. Their original misunderstanding of one another almost precludes them from discovering the common ground that ultimately transcends the class and status markers that divide them.</p>

<p><em>Lest Innocent Blood Be Shed: The Story of the Village of Le Chambon and How Goodness Happened There</em> by Phillip Halle is a researched account of a Huguenot (French Protestant) congregation in southern France that banded together with their community during World War II to smuggle Jews out of the country to safety. Inspired by their study of non-violent resistance, Pastor André Trocmé and the Le Chambon congregation, along with others from their community, organized a coordinated plan to care for Jewish refugees who fled from northern Nazi-occupied France, forge new passports for them, and then send them forth to others who would take them out of Europe.</p>

<p>André and spouse Magda Trocmé were designated Righteous among Nations by the State of Israel in 1971 and 1986, respectively, for their dedication to saving Jews during the Shoah. Their nephew, Daniel Trocmé was also named Righteous among Nations in 1976. He died in the Majdanek concentration camp in April 1944. The national Shoah memorial in Israel, Yad Vashem, also honors the village of Le Chambon-sur-Lignon and its neighboring communities with a monument on its grounds.</p>

<p>Hallie explains that the ethic of Pastor André Trocmé “drew its power from the life and death of Jesus. The example and the words of Jesus inspired awe in André Trocmé, and he did what he did because he wanted to be with Jesus, in the sense of imitating Jesus’ example and obeying his words . . . He wanted to be close to Jesus, a loving disciple who put his feet in Jesus’ footprints with stubborn devotion.” For me, Pastor André Trocmé and the congregation of Le Chambon are the embodiment of what it means to live in the model of Jesus, living out the biblical commandment to love our neighbors as ourselves.</p>

<p><em>Holidays and Holy Nights</em> by Christopher Hill traces the development of the liturgical calendar in Europe in order to explain how the cycles of nature and the pre-Christian traditions of the people of the countryside joined with established Christian practices to shape the design of the church year we know today. Hill poetically weaves together various traditions surrounding the most celebrated aspects of the church year, such as Advent and Holy Week, as well as introducing Protestants to lesser-known aspects of the liturgical calendar like Candlemas (Feb. 2nd) and Michaelmas (Sept. 29).</p>

<p>Hill gently persuades his readers to embrace the beauty of how pre-Christian seasonal practices meld with Christian traditions around the world in ways that can greatly enhance our spiritual lives. For example, Hill demonstrates that Halloween need not be perceived as something antithetical to Christianity, but rather as a celebration that allows us to face our fears with a sense of humor and engage in the ancient practice of offering hospitality to the stranger. For Hill, Halloween is the release of festive energy that has always preceded periods of fasting, like how Carnival/Mardi Gras is the precursor to Ash Wednesday. At the end of each chapter he provides suggestions for activities and spiritual practices that individuals, families, and congregations can use to integrate the rhythms of the liturgical year into our daily spiritual practices.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reading" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A few years ago I heard a radio interview on NPR with an author of a novel in which the narrator introduces each character in terms of three books that best describes him or her. I pondered this idea in search of three books that would form a composite image of who I am and what my values are. I selected Jane Austen’s Pride and Prejudice, Philip Halle’s Lest Innocent Blood Be Shed, and Christopher Hill’s Holidays and Holy Nights. Pride and Prejudice by Jane Austen is a novel of the British Regency period and is considered by many to be a great work of English literature. Like Jane Austen, I am simultaneously a romantic and a pragmatist. I love a happy ending, but I realize that happy endings are often hard won. For better and for worse, one’s choices in life are shaped by numerous familial, societal, and financial considerations. The novel’s hero, Elizabeth Bennett, possesses several qualities that I also see in myself. She is smart, clever, personable, persistent, and fiercely loyal. The original title of the novel was First Impressions, because it explores the relationship between our surface perceptions of other people upon first meeting them and the substance of the character that may reside underneath their public persona. Through the course of the novel Elizabeth Bennett and her romantic opposite, Fitzwilliam Darcy, discover that snap judgments can lead to false conclusions. Their original misunderstanding of one another almost precludes them from discovering the common ground that ultimately transcends the class and status markers that divide them. Lest Innocent Blood Be Shed: The Story of the Village of Le Chambon and How Goodness Happened There by Phillip Halle is a researched account of a Huguenot (French Protestant) congregation in southern France that banded together with their community during World War II to smuggle Jews out of the country to safety. Inspired by their study of non-violent resistance, Pastor André Trocmé and the Le Chambon congregation, along with others from their community, organized a coordinated plan to care for Jewish refugees who fled from northern Nazi-occupied France, forge new passports for them, and then send them forth to others who would take them out of Europe. André and spouse Magda Trocmé were designated Righteous among Nations by the State of Israel in 1971 and 1986, respectively, for their dedication to saving Jews during the Shoah. Their nephew, Daniel Trocmé was also named Righteous among Nations in 1976. He died in the Majdanek concentration camp in April 1944. The national Shoah memorial in Israel, Yad Vashem, also honors the village of Le Chambon-sur-Lignon and its neighboring communities with a monument on its grounds. Hallie explains that the ethic of Pastor André Trocmé “drew its power from the life and death of Jesus. The example and the words of Jesus inspired awe in André Trocmé, and he did what he did because he wanted to be with Jesus, in the sense of imitating Jesus’ example and obeying his words . . . He wanted to be close to Jesus, a loving disciple who put his feet in Jesus’ footprints with stubborn devotion.” For me, Pastor André Trocmé and the congregation of Le Chambon are the embodiment of what it means to live in the model of Jesus, living out the biblical commandment to love our neighbors as ourselves. Holidays and Holy Nights by Christopher Hill traces the development of the liturgical calendar in Europe in order to explain how the cycles of nature and the pre-Christian traditions of the people of the countryside joined with established Christian practices to shape the design of the church year we know today. Hill poetically weaves together various traditions surrounding the most celebrated aspects of the church year, such as Advent and Holy Week, as well as introducing Protestants to lesser-known aspects of the liturgical calendar like Candlemas (Feb. 2nd) and Michaelmas (Sept. 29). Hill gently persuades his readers to embrace the beauty of how pre-Christian seasonal practices meld with Christian traditions around the world in ways that can greatly enhance our spiritual lives. For example, Hill demonstrates that Halloween need not be perceived as something antithetical to Christianity, but rather as a celebration that allows us to face our fears with a sense of humor and engage in the ancient practice of offering hospitality to the stranger. For Hill, Halloween is the release of festive energy that has always preceded periods of fasting, like how Carnival/Mardi Gras is the precursor to Ash Wednesday. At the end of each chapter he provides suggestions for activities and spiritual practices that individuals, families, and congregations can use to integrate the rhythms of the liturgical year into our daily spiritual practices.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Statement of Faith</title><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//faith-statement/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Statement of Faith" /><published>2020-05-13T08:23:42+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T08:23:42+00:00</updated><id>https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//statement-of-faith</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//faith-statement/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="spiritual-autobiography-and-ministerial-identity">Spiritual Autobiography and Ministerial Identity</h2>

<p>I was raised in a moderate Baptist congregation, Central Baptist Church of Fountain City in Knoxville, TN. After a conversation with my family, I made a profession of faith at age seven and was baptized a few months later. My ministerial training began early in this nurturing and loving community that encouraged me to be an active participant in Bible study, worship planning and leadership, church committees, and local and global service. When I experienced a calling to ministry before my senior year of college, ministers and church members responded with joy and affirmation. They continued to love me and support me through my educational journey and graciously ordained me on July 14, 2002 following my graduation from divinity school. Central Baptist gave me the great gift of facilitating my vocational journey and teaching me the value of collaborative ministry.
<!--more--></p>

<p>While attending Wake Forest University Divinity School from 1999–2002, I developed a love of and facility for academic study of the Bible, which led me to further studies that culminated in my earning a Ph.D. in Biblical Interpretation from Brite Divinity School at Texas Christian University in May of 2016. For the past several years I have been living in Syracuse, NY where my spouse is pursuing his own Ph.D. in Religion. From the time I entered divinity school until the present, I have been living out my ministerial calling through both professional and volunteer ministry opportunities. In September of 2017, I began an interim pastorate at West Baptist Church in Oswego, NY. During this time I have discovered a great love for and a specific calling to pastoral ministry.</p>

<p>I understand my vocational identity in terms of a dual commitment to the church and the academy, though my ministerial identity has always been primary. I intentionally pursued my Ph.D. in a divinity school surrounded by professors and students who also shared these parallel commitments. My own spiritual formation has always been spurred through the creative synthesis of engagement in faith community and life in the classroom.</p>

<p><strong>Theology</strong></p>

<p>I believe in <strong>God</strong>, the Creator who breathed life into human beings in order to build a deep, abiding relationship with us. I believe that God is active in history and is constantly working to bring new life into being, particularly in places where it seems that all hope is lost. I believe that God’s ways are not coercive, but rather, God uses persuasive power to draw humanity in. We have free will and God waits for us to respond. God’s love for humanity is so great that God continues to wait on us, even though we fall short over and over again. Our task is to do justice, love kindness, and walk humbly with our Creator (see Micah 6:8).</p>

<p>I believe in <strong>Jesus</strong>, the incarnate son of God who shows us what it is to embody radical divine love. Christians are disciples who relate to God through Jesus, pray in his name, and interpret scripture in light of his example. Jesus shows us the way towards being the people God knows we can be. Even if we fall short, we still strive towards the Christ-like ideal. Jesus calls us back to God’s deepest desire for us, ‘“You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your mind” and “You shall love your neighbor as yourself” (see Matt 22:37–38).</p>

<p>I believe that the stories of Jesus’ birth, life, death, and resurrection are redemptive. In the resurrection God testifies to who Jesus is and to how divine power works. Human sin puts Jesus to death on the cross, but God responds by saying that ultimately death cannot and will not prevail. The crucifixion and resurrection bear witness to the fact that all humans experience pain, betrayal, and abandonment, but God never, ever leaves us that way.</p>

<p>I believe in the <strong>Holy Spirit</strong>, the holy gift that descends when Jesus ascends to God. The Holy Spirit is the enlivening divine presence within Christian community. While Jesus was on earth, the divine walked among us. After he ascended, Jesus’ disciples became the body of Christ. The Holy Spirit makes possible the transformative power of faith lived out in Christian community. The Holy Spirit sustains us, comforts us, and enables us to live out our divinely given callings both individually and collectively.</p>

<p>I believe in the <strong>Bible</strong>, the great narrative of God’s relationship with humanity, which teaches us the purpose of our creation and shapes who we are as people of faith. The Bible conveys identity and directs our actions by communicating the formative (Who are we?) and normative (What should we do?) values of spiritual lives and practice. The Bible shows us over and over again that God chooses the most unlikely people to fulfill  divine purposes. Those who are willing to take risks that build up the community of faith gain God’s blessing. Those who hold on to their possessions and are unwilling to share out of God’s abundance lose in this life and the next. The Bible teaches us that a life committed to love of God and neighbor may come at a high cost, but it is the key to a life worth having.</p>

<p>I affirm and wholeheartedly believe in the <strong>historic Baptist principles</strong> of Soul Freedom, Bible Freedom, Church Freedom, and Religious Freedom that bring Baptists together and sometimes require that we part ways. Baptists, at our best, respect individual autonomy balanced with the wisdom of local church bodies where the individual is known and loved. We believe that faith is best shared and accepted freely in a non-coercive atmosphere that demonstrates respect for all people. While some advocate that Christians need to move away from denominational affiliations, growing research shows that young Christians who are aware of the particularities of their Christian identity –– and the contributions of that identity to Christianity as a whole –– are more likely to stay engaged are less likely to drop out of church as they get older.</p>

<p>My understanding of <strong>Christian life and practice</strong> is that it is best lived out through individual commitment and corporate involvement. By listening and paying attention to one another as we study the Bible together, hear one another reflect, pray together, and serve together we come to recognize God’s presence in each other’s lives and help one another discern what God is calling us to do. I find great spiritual sustenance in tying my spiritual practices to the cycle of the liturgical year, which has been a vital development in my spiritual growth over the last several years. Additionally, I try to orient my life according to gratitude, taking time each day to recognize the big (family, friends, health, work that matters) and small things (fall leaves, spring flowers, sweet potatoes, local coffee, and a front porch to sit on) for which I am thankful. When I engage spiritual practices, whether walking a labyrinth, journaling, or crafting prayer books for the homebound, I make space for divine revelation in the everyday. One of my greatest joys is helping others find meaningful ways to develop spiritual practices that work for them in their lives.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ministry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Spiritual Autobiography and Ministerial Identity I was raised in a moderate Baptist congregation, Central Baptist Church of Fountain City in Knoxville, TN. After a conversation with my family, I made a profession of faith at age seven and was baptized a few months later. My ministerial training began early in this nurturing and loving community that encouraged me to be an active participant in Bible study, worship planning and leadership, church committees, and local and global service. When I experienced a calling to ministry before my senior year of college, ministers and church members responded with joy and affirmation. They continued to love me and support me through my educational journey and graciously ordained me on July 14, 2002 following my graduation from divinity school. Central Baptist gave me the great gift of facilitating my vocational journey and teaching me the value of collaborative ministry. While attending Wake Forest University Divinity School from 1999–2002, I developed a love of and facility for academic study of the Bible, which led me to further studies that culminated in my earning a Ph.D. in Biblical Interpretation from Brite Divinity School at Texas Christian University in May of 2016. For the past several years I have been living in Syracuse, NY where my spouse is pursuing his own Ph.D. in Religion. From the time I entered divinity school until the present, I have been living out my ministerial calling through both professional and volunteer ministry opportunities. In September of 2017, I began an interim pastorate at West Baptist Church in Oswego, NY. During this time I have discovered a great love for and a specific calling to pastoral ministry. I understand my vocational identity in terms of a dual commitment to the church and the academy, though my ministerial identity has always been primary. I intentionally pursued my Ph.D. in a divinity school surrounded by professors and students who also shared these parallel commitments. My own spiritual formation has always been spurred through the creative synthesis of engagement in faith community and life in the classroom. Theology I believe in God, the Creator who breathed life into human beings in order to build a deep, abiding relationship with us. I believe that God is active in history and is constantly working to bring new life into being, particularly in places where it seems that all hope is lost. I believe that God’s ways are not coercive, but rather, God uses persuasive power to draw humanity in. We have free will and God waits for us to respond. God’s love for humanity is so great that God continues to wait on us, even though we fall short over and over again. Our task is to do justice, love kindness, and walk humbly with our Creator (see Micah 6:8). I believe in Jesus, the incarnate son of God who shows us what it is to embody radical divine love. Christians are disciples who relate to God through Jesus, pray in his name, and interpret scripture in light of his example. Jesus shows us the way towards being the people God knows we can be. Even if we fall short, we still strive towards the Christ-like ideal. Jesus calls us back to God’s deepest desire for us, ‘“You shall love the Lord your God with all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your mind” and “You shall love your neighbor as yourself” (see Matt 22:37–38). I believe that the stories of Jesus’ birth, life, death, and resurrection are redemptive. In the resurrection God testifies to who Jesus is and to how divine power works. Human sin puts Jesus to death on the cross, but God responds by saying that ultimately death cannot and will not prevail. The crucifixion and resurrection bear witness to the fact that all humans experience pain, betrayal, and abandonment, but God never, ever leaves us that way. I believe in the Holy Spirit, the holy gift that descends when Jesus ascends to God. The Holy Spirit is the enlivening divine presence within Christian community. While Jesus was on earth, the divine walked among us. After he ascended, Jesus’ disciples became the body of Christ. The Holy Spirit makes possible the transformative power of faith lived out in Christian community. The Holy Spirit sustains us, comforts us, and enables us to live out our divinely given callings both individually and collectively. I believe in the Bible, the great narrative of God’s relationship with humanity, which teaches us the purpose of our creation and shapes who we are as people of faith. The Bible conveys identity and directs our actions by communicating the formative (Who are we?) and normative (What should we do?) values of spiritual lives and practice. The Bible shows us over and over again that God chooses the most unlikely people to fulfill  divine purposes. Those who are willing to take risks that build up the community of faith gain God’s blessing. Those who hold on to their possessions and are unwilling to share out of God’s abundance lose in this life and the next. The Bible teaches us that a life committed to love of God and neighbor may come at a high cost, but it is the key to a life worth having. I affirm and wholeheartedly believe in the historic Baptist principles of Soul Freedom, Bible Freedom, Church Freedom, and Religious Freedom that bring Baptists together and sometimes require that we part ways. Baptists, at our best, respect individual autonomy balanced with the wisdom of local church bodies where the individual is known and loved. We believe that faith is best shared and accepted freely in a non-coercive atmosphere that demonstrates respect for all people. While some advocate that Christians need to move away from denominational affiliations, growing research shows that young Christians who are aware of the particularities of their Christian identity –– and the contributions of that identity to Christianity as a whole –– are more likely to stay engaged are less likely to drop out of church as they get older. My understanding of Christian life and practice is that it is best lived out through individual commitment and corporate involvement. By listening and paying attention to one another as we study the Bible together, hear one another reflect, pray together, and serve together we come to recognize God’s presence in each other’s lives and help one another discern what God is calling us to do. I find great spiritual sustenance in tying my spiritual practices to the cycle of the liturgical year, which has been a vital development in my spiritual growth over the last several years. Additionally, I try to orient my life according to gratitude, taking time each day to recognize the big (family, friends, health, work that matters) and small things (fall leaves, spring flowers, sweet potatoes, local coffee, and a front porch to sit on) for which I am thankful. When I engage spiritual practices, whether walking a labyrinth, journaling, or crafting prayer books for the homebound, I make space for divine revelation in the everyday. One of my greatest joys is helping others find meaningful ways to develop spiritual practices that work for them in their lives.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pastoral note on COVID-19</title><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//covid/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pastoral note on COVID-19" /><published>2020-03-18T15:04:24+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-18T15:04:24+00:00</updated><id>https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//covid-closure</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//covid/"><![CDATA[<p>Dear Members and Friends of West Baptist Church,</p>

<p>The emergence of COVID-19 (Coronavirus) places us in the midsts of a health crisis unlike anything most of us have faced in our lifetimes. While we seek to protect our loved ones and ourselves against infection, we empathize with those who are ill and grieve with those who have suffered loss. Our continued prayers are with those directly affected by the virus, those in the health care community who are tirelessly working to treat the sick, and those government and public health officials developing responsive measures.
<!--more--></p>

<p>In accordance with government guidance that the public should avoid gatherings of 10 or more people, the West Baptist Church Council has decided to cancel worship for the next two Sundays (March 22 and March 29) with the hope that we will be able to gather again on Palm Sunday (April 5). We will post updates about worship and other church events on the church website westbaptistchurch.org. For those of you who do not have access to a computer, we will contact you by phone.</p>

<p>We are currently in the season of Lent on the church calendar, a 40 day period of preparation and contemplation that precedes Easter. Our scripture passages during this season have highlighted important encounters with Jesus that take place in the gospel of John. The scripture reading for March 22 is John 9:1-41 and the reading for March 29 is John 11:1-45. I hope you will read and meditate upon those passages even though we will be unable to gather together for worship.</p>

<p>Pay attention to the ways in which some people come to faith as a result of their experience with Jesus and others fear what they have difficulty understanding. What transformation or encouragement might God be working within you this Lenten season? What do these scriptures help us understand about what it means to be a disciple of Jesus?</p>

<p>May we seek to support each other (from an appropriate distance) during this challenging time. Please feel free to call me on my my cell phone or email me <a href="mailto:stephanie@stephaniewyatt.net">stephanie@stephaniewyatt.net</a> should you need a listening ear or some company.</p>

<p>Lenten blessings,</p>

<p>Pastor Stephanie</p>

<p>Rev, Stephanie M. Wyatt, Ph.D.<br />
<a href="http://stephaniewyatt.net/">stephaniewyatt.net</a></p>

<p><em>“For God has not given us a spirit of fear, but of power and of love and of a sound mind”</em> ~ 2 Timothy 1:7.</p>

<p>Solidarity Image by <a href="https://pixabay.com/">Gerd Altmann</a> from <a href="https://pixabay.com/?utm_source=link-attribution&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=image&amp;utm_content=4924028">Pixabay</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="pastor" /><category term="note" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Dear Members and Friends of West Baptist Church,]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//assets/images/splash/solidarity-4924028_1920.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//assets/images/splash/solidarity-4924028_1920.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Invited Sermons and Presentations</title><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//invited-sermons/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Invited Sermons and Presentations" /><published>2020-03-07T15:04:24+00:00</published><updated>2020-03-07T15:04:24+00:00</updated><id>https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//invited-sermons</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//invited-sermons/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li><em>First Baptist Church Murfreesboro,Tennessee</em> — “We’re All in This Together,” Sermon for the Martha Stearns Marshall Month of Preaching, February 19, 2017</li>
  <li><em>Robert Carr Chapel, Brite Divinity School at Texas Christian University</em> — “Christian Response-ability for‘Never Again,’” A Christian Service for Yom HaShoah: Remembering the Holocaust, January 25, 2011.</li>
  <li><em>Texas Christian University</em> — “This is ‘Myspace:’ Ending Violence Against Women Through Community,” Graduate Student Forum,Women’s History Month, February 2007.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sermons" /><category term="presentations" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[First Baptist Church Murfreesboro,Tennessee — “We’re All in This Together,” Sermon for the Martha Stearns Marshall Month of Preaching, February 19, 2017 Robert Carr Chapel, Brite Divinity School at Texas Christian University — “Christian Response-ability for‘Never Again,’” A Christian Service for Yom HaShoah: Remembering the Holocaust, January 25, 2011. Texas Christian University — “This is ‘Myspace:’ Ending Violence Against Women Through Community,” Graduate Student Forum,Women’s History Month, February 2007.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jezebel, Elijah, and the Widow of Zarephath</title><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//jezebel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jezebel, Elijah, and the Widow of Zarephath" /><published>2016-04-10T15:04:24+00:00</published><updated>2016-04-10T15:04:24+00:00</updated><id>https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//jezebel-elijah-widow-zarephath</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//jezebel/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="abstract">Abstract:</h2>

<p>This article offers a dialogical examination of 1 Kgs 17–19 that deconstructs traditionally accepted characterizations of Jezebel, Elijah, and the Widow of Zarephath. This study proposes that shifting emphasis from Elijah and Jezebel as polar opposites to a literary ménage à trois that involves all three characters makes it possible for the holy man to become a stranger and the strange women to become holy. The narrative tensions thus revealed question the validity of Israel’s definitive identity markers. When reading the stories of Jezebel, Elijah, and the Widow of Zarephath in the Deuteronomistic History, clear-cut distinctions between ‘insiders’ and ‘outsiders’ continually collapse.
<!--more--></p>

<p><a href="http://jot.sagepub.com/content/36/4/435.abstract"><img src="/assets/images/JSOT_F1.medium.gif" alt="Jezebel, Elijah, and the Widow of Zarephath: A Ménage à Trois that Estranges the Holy and Makes the Holy the Strange, JSOT" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Keywords</strong>: <em>Widows, Hebrew Bible, Old Testament, Feminist Biblical Interpretation</em> Stephanie Wyatt, “Jezebel, Elijah, and the Widow of Zarephath: A Ménage à Trois that Estranges the Holy and Makes the Holy the Strange,” <em>JSOT</em> 36.4, June 2012, 435-458. doi: <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/0309089212438020">10.1177/0309089212438020</a> </p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="scholarship" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Abstract: This article offers a dialogical examination of 1 Kgs 17–19 that deconstructs traditionally accepted characterizations of Jezebel, Elijah, and the Widow of Zarephath. This study proposes that shifting emphasis from Elijah and Jezebel as polar opposites to a literary ménage à trois that involves all three characters makes it possible for the holy man to become a stranger and the strange women to become holy. The narrative tensions thus revealed question the validity of Israel’s definitive identity markers. When reading the stories of Jezebel, Elijah, and the Widow of Zarephath in the Deuteronomistic History, clear-cut distinctions between ‘insiders’ and ‘outsiders’ continually collapse.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Philosophy of Ministry</title><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//ministry/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Philosophy of Ministry" /><published>2016-04-09T21:25:43+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-12T08:23:42+00:00</updated><id>https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//ministry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//ministry/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Ministry, in my mind, requires a collaborative effort on the part of members, leadership, and ministerial staff.</strong> The church is at its best when members feel invested in and integral to the life of the church. A flourishing congregation is one where ministers nurture and appreciate the active participation of the congregants in the life of the church. Ministers provide guidance, expertise, education, and worship leadership that both fulfills their own callings and speaks to the evolving needs of the congregation and the world beyond. <strong>I understand my ministerial role as that of equipping people of faith with the tools they need to craft lives of service and reflection in the church and in the world.</strong>
<!--more--></p>

<p>The church is the body of Christ on earth, a living testimony to God’s redemptive work in the birth, life, death, and resurrection of Jesus. The gospel holds within it the power to transform and call us to fresh ways to embody Christ’s presence in our own particular time and place. <strong>I believe in the power of the church as a community of diverse minds and hearts that come together around a desire to share life, explore faith, and minister together.</strong> Church should include both the inner movement towards spiritual formation and outward movement towards engaging the world in the model of Jesus. My understanding of Christian life and practice is that it is best lived out when individuals are part of a local church community where they can seek personal spiritual growth, participate in corporate worship and fellowship, and connect to the larger world through service.</p>

<p><strong>I gravitate towards narrative theology, which seeks to understand how our individual and collective stories intersect with the story of God, Jesus, and the Holy Spirit.</strong> Scripture and the church year are two powerful conduits for this type of theology. The Bible is an epic drama that depicts the divine-human relationship in all its absurdity and transcendence. It invites us to reflect on the normative and formative values that define who we are as people and as communities of faith. The church year draws us into regular cycles of contemplation, remembrance, and celebration as we reenact the stories of Jesus and the church.</p>

<p>Through worship, study, spiritual practices, and community gatherings, the church year helps us to find meaning in the various seasons of our lives.</p>

<p><strong>At its best, I believe the church should display a ‘safe place’ sign in relation to the local and global community.</strong> Many younger people have broken with the church because they have experienced judgment, rejection, and abuse from individual Christians and churches as institutions. The best thing we can do as Christians in this context is to live the gospel in its fullness – a gospel that does not condemn, but rather invites people into a relationship to God through Christ in concert with the Holy Spirit. We live out the gospel best when we engage others in loving ways that demonstrate our care for them, particularly for those who are hurting, who have limited financial means, and who have been burned by church.</p>

<p>Having grown up and served in a number of congregations where my relationships with church members of all ages were important to my spiritual development and vocational discernment, <strong>I deeply care about fostering opportunities for intergenerational education, social activities, and service projects.</strong> I believe that older generations have much to offer the younger generations in terms of sharing church history and personal experience, providing knowledge and wisdom, as well as helping them to develop a sense of belonging and purpose within the church. Younger members have much to teach the older generations in terms of embracing those who feel alienated from church life, moving towards a more authentic way of being real with one another, and bridging traditional sacred and secular boundaries.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="church-related-publications">Church Related Publications</h2>

<ul>
  <li>“The Blessing of the Womb: A Sermon for Early Advent,” in Sacred Seasons: Creative Worship Tools for Your Church (Advent/Christmastide 2005): 13–15. (<a href="/documents//Wyatt-Advent05-Manger.pdf">PDF</a>)</li>
  <li>“Each Generation Plays a Role in Preserving Baptist Heritage,” Report from the Capitol, May 14, 2003. (<a href="http://stephaniewyatt.net/documents/Wyatt_Each_generation_plays_a_role_in-preserving_Baptist_heritage.pdf">PDF</a>)</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ministry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ministry, in my mind, requires a collaborative effort on the part of members, leadership, and ministerial staff. The church is at its best when members feel invested in and integral to the life of the church. A flourishing congregation is one where ministers nurture and appreciate the active participation of the congregants in the life of the church. Ministers provide guidance, expertise, education, and worship leadership that both fulfills their own callings and speaks to the evolving needs of the congregation and the world beyond. I understand my ministerial role as that of equipping people of faith with the tools they need to craft lives of service and reflection in the church and in the world. The church is the body of Christ on earth, a living testimony to God’s redemptive work in the birth, life, death, and resurrection of Jesus. The gospel holds within it the power to transform and call us to fresh ways to embody Christ’s presence in our own particular time and place. I believe in the power of the church as a community of diverse minds and hearts that come together around a desire to share life, explore faith, and minister together. Church should include both the inner movement towards spiritual formation and outward movement towards engaging the world in the model of Jesus. My understanding of Christian life and practice is that it is best lived out when individuals are part of a local church community where they can seek personal spiritual growth, participate in corporate worship and fellowship, and connect to the larger world through service. I gravitate towards narrative theology, which seeks to understand how our individual and collective stories intersect with the story of God, Jesus, and the Holy Spirit. Scripture and the church year are two powerful conduits for this type of theology. The Bible is an epic drama that depicts the divine-human relationship in all its absurdity and transcendence. It invites us to reflect on the normative and formative values that define who we are as people and as communities of faith. The church year draws us into regular cycles of contemplation, remembrance, and celebration as we reenact the stories of Jesus and the church. Through worship, study, spiritual practices, and community gatherings, the church year helps us to find meaning in the various seasons of our lives. At its best, I believe the church should display a ‘safe place’ sign in relation to the local and global community. Many younger people have broken with the church because they have experienced judgment, rejection, and abuse from individual Christians and churches as institutions. The best thing we can do as Christians in this context is to live the gospel in its fullness – a gospel that does not condemn, but rather invites people into a relationship to God through Christ in concert with the Holy Spirit. We live out the gospel best when we engage others in loving ways that demonstrate our care for them, particularly for those who are hurting, who have limited financial means, and who have been burned by church. Having grown up and served in a number of congregations where my relationships with church members of all ages were important to my spiritual development and vocational discernment, I deeply care about fostering opportunities for intergenerational education, social activities, and service projects. I believe that older generations have much to offer the younger generations in terms of sharing church history and personal experience, providing knowledge and wisdom, as well as helping them to develop a sense of belonging and purpose within the church. Younger members have much to teach the older generations in terms of embracing those who feel alienated from church life, moving towards a more authentic way of being real with one another, and bridging traditional sacred and secular boundaries. Church Related Publications “The Blessing of the Womb: A Sermon for Early Advent,” in Sacred Seasons: Creative Worship Tools for Your Church (Advent/Christmastide 2005): 13–15. (PDF) “Each Generation Plays a Role in Preserving Baptist Heritage,” Report from the Capitol, May 14, 2003. (PDF)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Teaching &amp;#038; Scholarship</title><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//teaching/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Teaching &amp;#038; Scholarship" /><published>2016-04-09T16:36:14+00:00</published><updated>2016-04-09T16:36:14+00:00</updated><id>https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//teaching-scholarship</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//teaching/"><![CDATA[<p>“To me the willingness to change and be changed, to remain always open is a defining principle of intellectual life”
~Parker Palmer in <em>Teaching Community</em></p>

<p>In my experience, education has provided a profound source of joy, as well as opening me to realities of the world that grieve me deeply. Education has empowered me to make changes in my life, expose myself to new opportunities, and take on forms of activism I may have never discovered on my own. It has also made me a more empathetic person. Education provided a window into lives of people whose lives radically differed from my own, and I found their stories compelling, disturbing, and transformative.
<!--more--></p>
<hr />

<h2 id="teaching-philosophy">Teaching Philosophy</h2>

<p>Teaching and learning empower students to tell their own story, converse with the story of a discipline, and organize their own cognitive map for shaping their future story. By going through these dialogic processes students hone their thinking; integrate their beliefs, values, and commitments; and practice moral values. This teaching philosophy emerges from my own experience teaching in the church and the academy. I taught Biblical Hebrew for two semesters at Brite Divinity School and served as a teaching assistant for six semesters in an introductory undergraduate course, Understanding Religion: Texts &amp; Ideas (focusing on the Hebrew Bible), in the religion department at Texas Christian University. Additionally, I have advised and designed programming for graduate and undergraduate students in the Women in Science and Engineering (WiSE) program at Syracuse University over the past four years. In these various educational contexts I seek to teach students not what to think, but help them shape how they think. I encourage students to approach new information with openness, an inquiring mind, an empathetic heart, and a growing sense of what is important to them. At the introductory level I expect students to be able to read a text or an article and articulate the basics of what they have read, as well as key concepts discussed in class. By the end of the course I expect students to be able to offer a thoughtful analysis of course texts as well as a critical reflection of their own thoughts and ideas about the materials covered. I expect to see a consideration of ideas outside a student’s own perspective and a beginning recognition of how his or her perspective shapes the meaning derived from those ideas. I utilize lecture, discussion, class assignments, reflection papers, feedback, and personal meetings with students to accomplish these goals. Upper level classes take this approach to the next level: including a mixture of lecture and discussion, but at this stage students should be able to assert more than the basics of what they have read and the meanings they derive. Advanced students should synthesize concepts and develop a thoughtful, articulate, and well-supported argument. They should name and explore the “So What?” question. What difference do the concepts of the course make to them? How will they proceed differently or similarly in light of this new information? If they have come to a different conclusion on some issue at the end of the course, why has this change occurred? How will their interactions with readings, research, and discussion impact who they are as people, as professionals, as ethical actors, and as citizens? Ultimately, my goal is to teach students how to work through vital questions of existence so that they will develop a framework for dealing with the various decisions they will make going forward –– whether in the workforce, with their families and friends, in the public square, or within faith and community organizations. The question of what kind of humans we want to be, which is at the core of a liberal arts education, impacts all aspects of life from how we behave ethically in the workplace to how we negotiate chores in the household. I delight in leading and accompanying students as we explore these questions together.   <a href="/documents/SMWyatt_Teaching_Philosophy_4_9_2016.pdf">Stephanie Wyatt - Teaching Philosophy in PDF Format.</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="teaching" /><category term="scholarship" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“To me the willingness to change and be changed, to remain always open is a defining principle of intellectual life” ~Parker Palmer in Teaching Community In my experience, education has provided a profound source of joy, as well as opening me to realities of the world that grieve me deeply. Education has empowered me to make changes in my life, expose myself to new opportunities, and take on forms of activism I may have never discovered on my own. It has also made me a more empathetic person. Education provided a window into lives of people whose lives radically differed from my own, and I found their stories compelling, disturbing, and transformative.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome</title><link href="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//welcome/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome" /><published>2016-04-09T16:01:23+00:00</published><updated>2016-04-09T16:01:23+00:00</updated><id>https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.stephaniewyatt.net//welcome/"><![CDATA[<!--more-->
<p><a href="/assets/images/copyright_Clem10_MG_4496cw_stephanie_bg.jpg"><img src="/images/stephanie-wyatt-sq-copyright-clem_t_webb.png" alt="Stephanie M. Wyatt - © Clem T. Webb" /></a></p>

<p>Stephanie Wyatt earned her Ph.D. in the area of Hebrew Bible (Old Testament) from <a href="http://brite.edu/" title="Brite Divinity School at TCU - Home Page">Brite Divinity School</a> in Ft Worth, TX. Her dissertation is <em>Widows in the Memories of Biblical Israel.</em> A life-long Baptist and an ordained minister, she is passionate about biblical interpretation, Christian education, social justice, living sustainably, and healthy, yet delicious food. In her spare time Stephanie enjoys spending time with her significant other, Adam, participating in worship planning for her church, trying local restaurants, listening to folk, jazz, and blues, and aerobic dancing (Zumba). In beginning the job search process, she is looking for a position teaching undergraduates or seminary students how to be thoughtful citizens and sensitive biblical interpreters. Originally hailing from East Tennessee, she misses the mountains and Grainger County tomatoes, but enjoys exploring the fantastic art museums in Dallas/Ft Worth. Currently Stephanie resides in Syracuse, New York.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>